A Register of the Nikolai Dmitrievich Talberg Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Nikolai Dmitrievich Talberg Papers
1918-1967
2008C60
Hoover Institution Archives
(3 linear feet) 20 microfilm reels
Correspondence, writings, diaries, notes, and printed matter, relating to Russian history, the history of the Russian Orthodox Church, and Russian émigré affairs.
Tal'berg, N. D.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by Hoover Institution Archives in 2008
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
A portion of the collection is available on Microfilm
Location of Originals
In part, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, New York
Chronology
1886 July 10 Born, Korostyshev, Kiev guberniia, Russia
1907 Graduated, Imperatorskoe uchilishche pravovedeniia
1907-1917 Served, Ministry of Internal Affairs
1927 Author, Tserkovnyi Raskol
1929 Author, Sviataia Rus'
1950-1967 Professor, Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary, Jordanville, NY
1960 Author, Otechestvennaia byl': iubileinyi sbornik
1964 Author, Istoriia russkoi tserkvi Author, Istoriia khristianskoi tserkvi
1966 Author, K sorokalietiiu pagubnago evlogianskago raskola
1967 May 29 Died, Jordanville, NY
Scope and Content of Collection
These papers reflect the writings and research interests of Nikolai Talberg, a government official in pre-Revolutionary Russia and historian, writer, and professor in emigration. Among his writings are works related to late 19th and early 20th century history, partially based on his own reminiscences and those of others. Major themes include the history of the Russian Orthodox Church, politics and contemporary issues of the Russian diaspora.
The SUBJECT FILE includes materials on the history of the Russian Orthodox Church and especially on the various jurisdictional conflicts that affected the Church in emigration. Particularly important are the documents dating from 1945 onwards relating to such conflicts in the United States. Of special significance is the correspondence of Archbishop Vitalii Maksimenko with representatives of different dioceses, parishes and organizations.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Holy Trinity Orthodox Seminary Archives as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is appended to this register. Any views, findings, conclusions or recommendations expressed in these materials do not necessarily represent those of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
Biography
Nikolai Dmitrievich Talberg was born in Korostyshev, Russia, on July 10, 1886. B His family, of Swedish origin, moved to Russia from Finland during the reign of Catherine the Great. Both his father and grandfather were affiliated with Kiev University. Talberg studied at the Imperatorskoe uchilishche pravovedeniia, graduating with a gold medal in 1907. For the next ten years he served in the Ministry of Internal Affairs.
In 1917, after the Russian Revolution, Talberg moved to the Caucasus but returned to Petersburg the same year and joined a secret monarchist organization headed by N. E. Markov. In 1919, Talberg left Russia, arriving in Berlin in 1920, where he continued to be affiliated and actively involved in Markov’s monarchist organization, the Vysshii monarkhicheskii sovet.
With his move to Belgrade, Talberg also became more involved with the Russian Orthodox Church outside Russia, eventually moving to the United States, where he accepted a teaching position at Holy Trinity Seminary in Jordanville, New York. Talberg authored several history textbooks, some still in use today at theological seminaries. He also published widely on Russian secular and church history.
Nikolai Dmitrievich Talberg died on May 29, 1967, in Jordanville, New York.
Russia--History.; Russia--Religion.; Russians--United States.; Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'.
- Biographical File, 1928-1966. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes address book, autobiographical sketch, clippings, correspondence, identification card, and immigration documents. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Address book, n.d. (Folder 1: 1)
  - Application form for Social Security, 1956-1957. (Folder 1: 2)
    Includes income tax returns
  - Autobiographical sketch, n.d. (Folder 1: 3)
  - Clippings about Talberg
    - 1928-1954 (Folder 1: 4)
    - 1955-1957 (Folder 1: 5)
    - 1958-1966 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Fiftieth anniversary of Talberg's graduation file
    - Clippings, 1957 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Congratulatory letters and telegrams, 1957 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Identification card, 1941 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Immigration documents, 1950 (Folder 1: 10)
- Diaries, 1953-1967.
  Arranged chronologically
  - 1953-1955 (Folder 1: 11)
  - 1956-1962 (Box 2)
  - 1963-1967 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1950-1967. (Box 4)
  General note
  See also Biographical File/Fiftieth anniversary of Talberg's graduation file
  Cards and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - General, 1950-67 and undated (Folder 4: 1)
  - Unidentified, 1965 and undated (Folder 4: 2)
  - Aleksandrov, Petr, 1960 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Byrnes, Robert F., 1959 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Fisher, Ekaterina, n.d. (Folder 4: 5)
  - Gershel'man, A., 1966 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Golokhvastov, Georgii, 1954 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Kol'tsov-Mosal'skii, Aleksandr Georgievich, 1956. (Folder 4: 8)
    Includes attachments relating to Archpriest Mikhail Pol'skii
  - Kulikovskii, Tikhon, 1952 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Lyons, Marvin, 1965 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Meshchaninov, V.
    See WRITINGS BY OTHERS/Meshchaninov
  - Nikita Aleksandrovich, Grand Duke, 1952 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Orem, S., 1954 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Russian Ecclesiastical Mission, 1958 (Folder 4: 13)
- Speeches and Writings, 1920-1966.
  Articles, clippings, drafts, pamphlets, and speeches, arranged chronologically by title
  - General
    - Magazine articles, 1920-1963.
      Mainly entire issues
      - General
        - 1920-1952. (Folder 4: 14)
          Includes articles in Dvuglavyi orel, Dietstvo vo Khristie, Vera i zhizn' (Salzburg, Austria), Obozrenie (Kellerberg, Austria), Pravoslavnyi blagoviestnik, Pravoslavnoe slovo
        - 1953-1963. (Folder 4: 15)
          Includes articles in Vladimirskii viestnik, Sviato-Vladimirskii put', Shkol'nik, Tserkovnoe slovo
      - Nashi vesti, 1954-1963 (Folder 4: 16)
    - Newspaper articles, 1936-1966
      - General. Mainly Rossiia and Russkaia zhizn'
        - 1936-1949 (Folder 4: 17)
        - 1951-1954 (Box-folder 5: 1)
        - 1955-1959 (Folder 5: 2)
        - 1960-1964 (Folder 5: 3)
        - 1965-1966 (Folder 5: 4)
      - Pravoslavnaia Rus', 1939-1940 (Folder 5: 5)
      - Russkoe slovo, 1957-1966 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Notes, n.d. (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Speeches, 1952 and undated (Folder 6: 2)
  - "Khronologiia tserkovnykh sobytii v Rossii i zagranitsei s 1917 g.,", n.d. (Folder 6: 3)
    Typescript
  - "Monastyri i ikh nasel'niki v Rossii,", n.d.
    - Background materials (Folder 6: 4)
    - Typescript (Folder 6: 5)
  - "Ocherki iz istorii vzaimootnoshenii Rossii s evropeiskimi gosudarstvami,", n.d. (Folder 6: 6)
    Printed copy
  - "Osviedomlenie k deviatomu vseamerikanskomu soboru,", n.d. (Folder 6: 7)
  - "Rossiia-spasitel'nitsa evropy v nachale XX vieka,", n.d. (Folder 6: 8)
  - Russian Church History (in Russian), n.d. (Folder 6: 9)
  - "Russkaia Zarubezhnaia Tserkov',", n.d. (Folder 6: 10)
  - Untitled article on international affairs, n.d. (Folder 6: 11)
    Holograph
  - Untitled article relating to Russian displaced persons (Folder 6: 12)
  - Untitled writing on the history of Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov' Zagranitsei, n.d. (Folder 6: 13)
  - Untitled memoir of Metropolitans Antonii (Khrapovitskii) and Anastasii (Gribanovskii), and Serbian Patriarchs Varnava (Rosich) and Gavrila and others. (Folder 6: 14)
  - "Vseobshchaia istoriia Tserkvi,", n.d. (Folder 6: 15)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Iz istoricheskoi kopilki," Rossiia, 1938, 39 (?). (Folder 6: 16)
  - "Turetskii vopros," Rossiia, 1939 December 14. (Folder 6: 17)
  - "Tam, gde sluzhat Rossii," Rossiia, 1939 December 24-31. (Folder 6: 18)
  - Istoriia Rossii, 1946. (Folder 7: 1)
  - Istoriia Russkoi Tserkvi, 1947. (Folder 7: 2)
  - "K tridtsatiletiiu ekaterinburgskogo zlodeianiia,", 1948 July 18. (Folder 7: 3)
  - Letter to the editor, Salzburger Nachrichten, 1949. (Folder 7: 4)
  - "Sila dukha i voli," Rossiia, 1950 November 25. (Folder 7: 5)
  - "Riedieiut riady," Rossiia, 1951 July 24. (Folder 7: 6)
  - "Velikii podvizhnik sviatoi Rusi," Rossiia, 1951 September 7. (Folder 7: 7)
  - "SShA i podlinnaia Rossiia," Rossiia, 1951 September 8. (Folder 7: 8)
  - "Vernyi sluga velikoi Rossii," Rossiia, 1951 September 18-19. (Folder 7: 9)
  - "Nebol'shaia popravka," Rossiia, 1952 May 20. (Folder 7: 10)
  - "Pomen'she legkomysliia v otsienkie istoricheskikh lichnostei i sobytii," Rossiia, 1952 June 14-18; Russkaia zhizn', 1952 June 18. (Folder 7: 11)
  - "Tsarskaia Rossiia i amerikanskaia demokratiia v ikh istorichesk. druzhestvennosti," Rossiia, 1952 June 21-24. (Folder 7: 12)
  - "K 140 liet. borodinskago srazheniia," Rossiia, 1952 September 11. (Folder 7: 13)
  - "Vostanovlenie istyny," Rossiia, 1952 October 20. (Folder 7: 14)
  - "K 500-lietiiu padeniia Vtorogo Rima,", 1953. (Folder 7: 15)
    Printed copy and typescript inserts
  - "Oplot protivokommunizma v Evrope," Rossiia, 1953 April 29. (Folder 7: 16)
  - "Sinman Ri," Rossiia, 1953 July 11. (Folder 7: 17)
  - "Vozstanovleniie istiny," Rossiia, 1953 October 20. (Folder 7: 18)
  - "Kogda Rossiia okhraniala mir v mire," Rossiia, 1953 November 13. (Folder 7: 19)
  - "Borets s silami razrusheniia," Rossiia, 1953 November 24. (Folder 7: 20)
  - Prostrannyi miesiatseslov sviatykh v Zemlie Rossiiskoi prosiiavshikh, 1954. (Folder 7: 21)
    Reviews of. Printed copy
  - "Trekhsotletie vossoedeneniia Malorossii," Rossiia, 1954 January 21-22; Russkaia Zhizn', 1954 January 27-29. (Folder 7: 22)
  - "Otstaivanie tsarem Rossii," Rossiia, 1954 March 4-5. (Folder 7: 23)
  - "Sorvannaia levymi pobeda," Russkaia zhizn', 1954 March 5-10. (Folder 7: 24)
  - "K stolietiiu vostochnoi voiny," Rossiia, 1954 March 18-24. (Folder 7: 25)
  - "V zaputavsheisia Frantsii," Rossiia, 1954 July 22. (Folder 7: 26)
  - "Proryv gosudarstvennoi plotiny," Rossiia, 1954 July 28-29. (Folder 7: 27)
  - "V tikhoi obiteli," Rossiia, 1954 September 9. (Folder 7: 28)
  - "Pamiati imperatora Pavla I," Rossiia, 1954 October 2. (Folder 7: 29)
  - "Pamiati viernago druga Rossii," Rossiia, 1954 October 9. (Folder 7: 30)
  - "Nazidatel'noe vospominanie," Rossiia, 1954 November 5. (Folder 7: 31)
  - "V smutie ubiennyi," Rossiia, 1954 November 10. (Folder 7: 32)
  - "Tsar'-mirotvorets," Rossiia, 1954 November 23-25. (Folder 7: 33)
  - "Deviatoe ianvaria," Rossiia, 1955 January 27-28. (Folder 7: 34)
  - "Iaroslav mudryi," Rossiia, 1955 February 2. (Folder 7: 35)
  - "Viernyi gosudariu i otechestvu," Rossiia, 1955 February 3. (Folder 7: 36)
  - "Nebol'shoe dopolnenie," Rossiia, 1955 February 18. (Folder 7: 37)
    Printed copy. Includes letters to editor regarding the article
  - "K piatidesiatiletiiu ubiistva velikago kniazia Sergiia Aleksandrovicha," Rossiia, 1955 February 25-26. (Folder 7: 38)
  - "Tridtsatilietnee sluzhenie tsaria Rossii: k stolietiiu konchiny imperatora Nikolaia I," Rossiia, 1955 March 5-10. (Folder 7: 39)
  - "Iz istoricheskoi kopilki," Russkaia zhizn', 1955 March 30-April 5. (Folder 7: 40)
  - "Iz istoricheskoi kopilki," Russkaia zhizn', 1955 September 7. (Folder 7: 41)
  - "K piatidesiatiletiiu portsmutskago mira," Rossiia, 1955 November 9-10. (Folder 7: 42)
  - "V preddverii pervago tragicheskago oktiabria," Rossiia, 1955 November 19-22. (Folder 7: 43)
  - "Otryv ot istoricheskikh kornei," Russkaia zhizn', 1955 December 13-16. (Folder 7: 44)
  - "Otryv ot istoricheskikh kornei," Rossiia, 1955 December 21-28. (Folder 7: 45)
  - Skorbnyi iubilei, 1956. (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - "Verkhovnyi kormchii beretsia za rul'," Rossiia, 1956 April 3-11. (Folder 8: 2)
  - "1905-yi god: revoliutsionnoe dvizhenie na ushcherbie," Russkaia zhizn', 1956 February 14-16; Rossiia, 1956 June 22-28. (Folder 8: 3)
  - "Izbranniki revoliutsii," Rossiia, 1956 July 11-17. (Folder 8: 4)
  - "Iz istoricheskoi kopilki," Rossiia, 1956 August 23. (Folder 8: 5)
  - "Tsarskaia milost'," Rossiia, 1956 October 17. (Folder 8: 6)
  - "K rodnym istokam," Rossiia, 1956 November 28. (Folder 8: 7)
  - "Imperator Nikolai I i Vengriia," Rossiia, 1956 November 29-December 4. (Folder 8: 8)
  - "1906 god: v preddverii gos. dumy," Rossiia, 1956 December 18-19. (Folder 8: 9)
  - "Na sluzhbie monarkhii," Rossiia, 1957 January 17. (Folder 8: 10)
  - "Gosudarevy preobrazovaniia i tverdost'," Rossiia, 1957 March 13-16. (Folder 8: 11)
  - "Svietloe torzhestvo," Rossiia, 1957 March 23. (Folder 8: 12)
  - "Sram: k sorokaletiiu revoliutsii," Rossiia, 1957 March 29-April 3. (Folder 8: 13)
  - "Muzh viernosti i razuma," Rossiia, 1957 April 30-May 10; Russkaia zhizn', 1957 May 25-June 1. (Folder 8: 14)
  - "Tsarskaia zabotlivost' ob invalidakh," Russkaia zhizn', 1957 September 21. (Folder 8: 15)
  - "Iz istoricheskoi kopilki," Rossiia, 1957 September 27-28. (Folder 8: 16)
  - "Nezabyvaemoe dorogoe proshloe," Rossiia, 1957 October 12. (Folder 8: 17)
  - "Otpor kramol'nikam," Rossiia, 1957 November 1. (Folder 8: 18)
  - "Revoliutsionnyi gnoinik," Rossiia, 1957 November 30-December 14; Russkaia Zhizn', 1958 January 29-February 6. (Folder 8: 19)
  - "1907 god," Rossiia, 1958 January 21-25. (Folder 8: 20)
  - "Priamoi zhiznennyi put'," Rossiia, 1958 March 28; Russkaia zhizn', March 20-27. (Folder 8: 21)
  - "Zabytoe v napominanie," Rossiia, 1958 April 2. (Folder 8: 22)
  - "'Besy' dvoinye agenty - strel'ba po svoim," Rossiia, 1958 April 3-11; Russkaia zhizn', 1958 April 24-May 15. (Folder 8: 23)
  - "Pamiati gosudaria," Rossiia, 1958 May 21. (Folder 8: 24)
  - "Gosudar' v rodnoi srede," Rossiia, 1958 June 1958. (Folder 8: 25)
  - "Mitropolit Anastasii: k 60-letiiu ego sviashchennosluzheniia," Rossiia, 1958 August 23-26. (Folder 8: 26)
  - "Arkhiepiskop Vitalii," Rossiia, 1958 August 23-26; Russkaia zhizn', 1958 September 9. (Folder 8: 27)
  - "Prolog ekaterinburgskoi tragedii," Russkaia zhizn', 1958 August 26-29; Rossiia, 1958 August 29-September 5. (Folder 8: 28)
  - "Vernye gosudariu ministry," Rossiia, 1958 September 25-October 2. (Folder 8: 29)
  - "Poiasnenie k sobytiiam 1905 goda," Rossiia, 1958 December 11. (Folder 8: 30)
  - "Na gosudarevoi sluzhbie," Rossiia, 1959 December 19-24. (Folder 8: 31)
  - "Iz istoricheskoi kopilki," Rossiia, 1959 December 25-29. (Folder 8: 32)
  - "Sviatye ravnoapostol'nye Mefodii i Kirill, pervouchiteli slavianskie,", [1963]. (Folder 8: 33)
  - "Imperator Nikolai I v svietie istoricheskoi pravdy,", 1964. (Folder 8: 34)
- OTECHESTVENNAIA BYL' FILE, 1960. (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
  Typescript with handwritten corrections
- WRITINGS BY OTHERS, 1922-1957 and undated (Box 10)
  - Unidentified
    - "Patriarshestvo v Rossii,", n.d. (Folder 10: 1)
    - Sermons, 1922-1929 and undated. (Folder 10: 2)
    - Untitled draft of a book on the history of the Russian Orthodox Church in the USSR from 1917-1927, n.d. (Folder 10: 3)
    - "Vokrug sekt i eresei: obshchii obzor russkoi viery,", n.d. (Folder 10: 4)
  - Iakhontov, Arkadii Nikolaevich
    - "Pervyi god voiny 1914 g,", 1935-1936. (Folder 10: 5)
      Typescript. Includes excerpts from related correspondence
    - "Tiazhelye dni," Arkhiv Russkoi Revoliutsii, 1926
      - Correspondence (Folder 10: 6)
      - Typescript (Folder 10: 7-8)
  - Ivanovskii, E., "Russkaia istoriia,", 1946. (Folder 10: 9)
    Printed copy (Salzburg, Austria)
  - Meshchaninov, V., [various articles], 1951-1957. (Folder 10: 10)
    Typescript. Includes related correspondence
  - Nedzielnitskii, Ioann, Protopresbyter, "Istoriia Russkoi Pravoslavnoi Tserkvi v Amerike,", 1945. (Folder 10: 11-12)
  - Pomazansky, Michael, Protopresbyter, "Kratkii ocherk istorii Russkoi Tserkvi,", n.d. (Folder 10: 13)
  - Sen-Vensan, A., "Na nivie Bozhiei,", n.d. (Folder 10: 14)
    typescript
- SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1960. (Box 11)
  Brochures, clippings, correspondence, notes, schedules, and syllabi
  - Arkhiepiskopiia Pravoslavnykh Russkikh Tserkvei v Zapadnoi Evrope, Ekzarkhat Vselenskogo Patriarkhata, 1945-1954 (Folder 11: 1)
  - Goremykin, Ivan Longinovich (Folder 11: 2)
  - Holy Trinity Seminary (Jordanville, NY)
    - General, 1949-1954. (Folder 11: 3)
      Includes 1950 course catalogue
    - Teaching materials.
      Includes schedules, syllabi, etc.
      - Dogmatic theology (Folder 11: 4)
      - Ecclesiastical history
        - General (Folder 11: 5)
        - Russian (Folder 11: 6)
      - Russian history. (Folder 11: 7)
        Includes lecture notes, study materials, curricula, examination
      - Russian literature (Folder 11: 8)
      - World history (Folder 11: 9)
  - Imperatorskoe uchilishche pravovedeniia--Alumni association. (Folder 11: 10)
    Includes correspondence and lists of members
  - Nicholas II, 1957 (Folder 11: 11)
  - Nikolaev, Konstantin Nikolaevich, 1949-1961. (Folder 11: 12)
    Includes his correspondence with Archbishop Averky Taushev, Bishop Nikon Rklitskii, Protopresbyter Pavel Kalinovich and others, writings
  - Nikolai Nikolaevich, Grand Duke of Russia (Folder 11: 13)
  - Orthodox Eastern Church. (Folder 11: 14)
    Includes biographical notes on Church fathers, notes on liturgical calendar of 1941, "Voskresnyi listok," and clippings
  - Refugee camps--Parsch, Austria (Folder 11: 15)
  - Rossiiskoe vremennoe natsional'noe pravitel'stvo, 1951 and undated (Folder 11: 16)
  - Russia--History--February Revolution, 1917. (Box-folder 12: 1)
    Includes declaration of Grand Duke Kirill Vladimirovich to the sailors of the Garde Equipage
  - Russians
    - Chile (Folder 12: 2)
    - Tubabao, Philippines (Folder 12: 3)
  - Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov
    - Exarchate of the Moscow Patriarchate in Western Europe, 1953-1958 and undated (Folder 12: 4)
    - History
      - 1918-1929. (Folder 12: 5)
        Materials relating to the destruction of relics and other objects of veneration
      - 1920 (Folder 12: 6)
      - 1922. (Folder 12: 7)
        Materials relating to Church administration in Russia and abroad
      - 1926-1948. (Folder 12: 8)
        Includes typescript about Metropolitan Petr of Krutitsa and various clippings
  - Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov Zagranitsei--History
    - General, 1924-1955 (Folder 12: 9)
    - Evlogii, Metropolitan. (Folder 12: 10)
      Relates to the establishment of Arkhiepiskopiia Pravoslavnykh Russkikh Tserkvei v Zapadnoi Evrope
    - Khram-pamiatnik v Briussele, 1949-1951 (Folder 12: 11)
    - Platon, Metropolitan, 1920-1934. (Box-folder 13: 1)
      Relates to the church affairs in the USA and the establishment of the North American Metropolitan District
    - Russian Orthodox Greek Catholic Church of America
      - General
        - General, 1945-1949 and undated. (Folder 13: 2)
          Includes court documents relating to St. Nicholas Cathedral, New York, NY
        - Los Angeles, 1937-1951 (Folder 13: 3)
      - Correspondence
        - Konstantin, Arkhimandrit (Zaitsev, Kirill Iosifovich) (Folder 13: 4)
        - Vitalii, Archbishop
          - General – Administrative, 1934-1947 (Folder 13: 5)
          - 1946 (Folder 13: 6)
          - 1947 (Folder 13: 7)
      - Printed matter
        - Brochures, leaflets, pamphlets, 1946-1955 and undated (Folder 13: 8)
        - Clippings
          - 1941-1953 and undated (Folder 14: 1)
          - 1954-1960 (Folder 14: 2)
  - Ukraine (Folder 14: 3)
  - Miscellany, 1939-1954 and undated. (Folder 14: 4)
    Relates primarily to Russian émigrés, politics and culture
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1957 and undated
  - General, 1957 and undated. (Folder 14: 5)
    Three prints, including one portrait of Archimandrite Iliia
  - Elena Vladimirovna, Grand Duchess, 1957. (Folder 14: 6)
    Three prints of her burial and associated list of attendees
  - Icons, n.d. (Folder 14: 7)
    Not filmed
  - Nicholas II, n.d. (Folder 14: 8)
    One original negative and numerous paper reprints and published illustrations. Not filmed
- PRINTED MATTER, 1927-1967. (Box 15-16)
  Clippings from various émigré newspapers and some German press relating to general topics as well as the Imperial Russian Navy, religion, and Russian history and culture. Not filmed. Originals retained by Holy Trinity Seminary
- RESEARCH NOTES, n.d. (Box 17-18)
  Citations, chronologies, compilations of quotes, jottings, and similar unsorted notes, mainly on scraps of paper, collected by Talberg in the course of his teaching and writing. Not filmed. Originals retained by Holy Trinity Seminary